<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defiance to death Being the funebrious commemoration of the Right Honourable, Baptist Lord Hickes, Viscount Camden, late deceased. Preached at Camden in Gloucester-shire, Nouember 8. 1629. By Iohn Gaule.</title>
            <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102991</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838750</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838750</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1066:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defiance to death Being the funebrious commemoration of the Right Honourable, Baptist Lord Hickes, Viscount Camden, late deceased. Preached at Camden in Gloucester-shire, Nouember 8. 1629. By Iohn Gaule.</title>
                  <author>Gaule, John, 1604?-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, [22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper, for Robert Allot, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Blacke Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-C¹²  *² .</note>
                  <note>Usually found bound with his: Practique theories: or, votive speculations upon Abrahams entertainment of the three angels.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Campden, Baptist Hicks, --  Viscount, 1551-1629.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFIANCE TO DEATH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being</hi> The Funebrious Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>Baptiſt</hi> Lord <hi>Hickes,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Camden,</hi> late deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>Camden</hi> in <hi>Glouce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſhire,</hi> Nouember 8. 1629.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> IOHN GAVLE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper,</hi> for <hi>Robert Allot,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Blacke Beare, 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:2"/>
            <head>To the truely Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and religious Ladies, <hi>Iulian,</hi> Viſcounteſſe <hi>Camden,</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> Lady <hi>Cooper;</hi> Daughters to the late right Honourable <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> Lord <hi>Hickes,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Camden;</hi> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of both this, and the life to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Noble, and vertuous Ladies:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O whom ſhould I dedicate the memoriall of your deceaſed Father, but to you, in whom he liues? Who (mee thinkes)
<pb facs="tcp:3138:3"/>but his Monuments, may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge his commemoration? Beſides the life hee was perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally poſſeſſed of; you are his deriued life: and he yet liues, (and long may he) though not in himſelfe, yet in his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Yet (alas!) how much rather had you (I know) to haue ſtill enioyed, then thus ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his life? But you are not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, how nature abides not alwayes, but ſucceedes: how God but lends, not bindes your friends to your inioyment. He was giuen you, to be taken from you: yours hee was, to vſe, rather then poſſeſſe: yours in his life, name, vertues, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to inherit; and not yours, in an earthly being to ingroſſe. Therefore had you him, to loſe him, and muſt therefore be contented with his loſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:3138:3"/>yea, ought indeed to reioyce ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that once yee had him; then ſorrow, that now ye haue him not. Grant, it cannot bee but a griefe to miſſe him: ſo neither but a ioy to remember him. It was an happineſſe more delighting, when you might reioyce in his preſence: but is an happineſſe more laſting, that you may yet reioyce in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. You both (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the common lot and hap) were much, and long happy, in a double Parent: the loſſe of one now admoniſhes, yea, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaudes you, to eſteeme another Parent, and feare anothers loſse. But, I ſpare from further repetitions of your loſse; leſt (while I would ſtriue to conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and appeaſe them) I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prooue but to renew your ſorrow; &amp; prouoke your feare.
<pb facs="tcp:3138:4"/>For mine owne part (who rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon my ſelfe not the leaſt in his loſse) I count it euen as enuy, to bewayle the happy: and but folly, forlornely to ſorrow for him; that certainly reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for himſelfe. Neuertheleſse (for loſse of friends) forbid I no man to mourne, but mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, and deſpaire. Such our ſorrowes, are but the late to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of our loue, and muſt as wel be moderate, as vnfaigned. Neither ſhould our hearts (in this caſe) be flinty, nor effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: nor our eyes alwayes dropping, nor altogether dry. For me, I like neither to bee niggardly, nor prodigall of my teares: neither to be deſperate, nor ambitious of my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints. I ſay no more of this ſorrow and loſse, becauſe I would not packe them vp, or
<pb facs="tcp:3138:4"/>decke them vp in words onely. Thus much haue I written, becauſe I would not that a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houre ſhould extinguiſh or ingroſse them. What I haue herein preſumed, beſides the comfort (I truſt) you ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by it: this alſo ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort mee, that you daigne to receiue it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your good Ladiſhips in all humble obſeruance, IOHN GAVLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3138:5"/>
            <head>A DEFIANCE TO DEATH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 15.55.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Oh death, where is thy ſting?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pright <hi>Adam</hi> was made im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall: but ſinfull <hi>Adam</hi> begat all his Sonnes mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, like as hee had made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3138:6"/>
               <hi>Adam</hi> then is dead, and ſo all <hi>Adams</hi> Sonnes but liue to dye. The ſentence of death paſt vpon vs in him; wee are but borne to the execution thereof in our ſelues. Euen as <hi>Adam</hi> himſelfe, for the neceſſity of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> dyed the ſame day that hee ſinned; though, for the euent, and iſſue of death, hee liued an hundred and thirty yeares after that day.<note place="margin">Gen. 5.5.</note> So in him wee vnderwent the ſame neceſſity; though it be for thouſands of yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that wee are brought out to ſuch an euent. As a Malefactor is a dead man according to the law, at that inſtant the ſentence is pronounced vpon him: though for ſome few dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the execution be deferred: So according to Gods law and decree, we are all dead in <hi>Adams</hi> doome: though God bee yet pleaſed to prolong thoſe things of ours, wherein we muſt liue to dye, accordingly as hee hath
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3138:6"/>doomed vs. A malefactor is not executed ſometimes of one, two, three, foure, fiue, or ſixe dayes after his iudgement: Euen ſo were we all adiudged to dye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee were; but God (with whom a thouſand yeeres is but as one day) hath appoynted the firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, or ſixt thouſand yeare of the world, to be the day of our exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>There is a more neceſſity vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our death, then our life. No ſuch need, that hee that is not, ſhould be, as that he that now liues, ſhould once dye.</p>
            <p>The former may be ſuppoſed, but this other is expreſſed: <hi>It is appoynted for all men once to dye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> There is alwaies a more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the End, then Meanes. Not onely in execution, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, is death the end of life. <hi>Mortinati ſumus,</hi> wee are borne to dye, and dye from the time that we are borne. Our birthday,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3138:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3138:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3138:8"/>what is it, but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our death-day? our death-day, what, but the end of our birth day? our birth-day precedes, or happens before our death-day: but our death-day is preferred before our birth-day: <hi>The day of death is better then the day that one is borne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.3</note> Did wee ſo conſider it, our birth-day is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a puniſhment, and our death-day (in compariſon) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Vt ſuppliciam non ſit naſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, mors efficit.</hi> Death is as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt the miſeries of life: and to dye, is but to reſt from thoſe labours, and ceaſe from thoſe ſorrowes, whereunto wee were borne. What a plague and puniſhment were our birth-day into a ſinfull and miſerable world, did not our death-day giue an end to all ſuch euils, both of ſinne, and paine?</p>
            <p>I ſaid, our birth-day is the beginning of our death-day: and our death-day but the end of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3138:8"/>our birth-day. We are deceiued, to call the day of our departure onely, the day of our death. On our laſt day indeed we ceaſe to liue, but from our firſt day, wee beginne to dye. <hi>Conſummat hora mortem extrema, non facit.</hi> Our laſt day doth not cauſe death, but conſummate it, doth rather finiſh, then beginne it. It is not the extream and vtmoſt minute of our life, that brings death vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: it rather but manifeſts, that death was alwayes with vs. As ſpake the Prophet of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Wee are killed all the day long,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 44.22 1 Cor. 15.31.</note> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> concerning his owne ſufferings, <hi>I dye daily:</hi> So, though no violence come againſt vs, euen through natures owne frailty, wee dye daily, and by fatall mortality, we are killed all the day long. We dye daily, from the time we firſt beginne to liue: On our firſt day, our life is the longeſt: euery day after, takes one day from our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3138:9"/>liues; and the longer wee haue liued, the leſſe we haue to liue. <hi>Quotidie morimur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec. lib. <hi>3.</hi> epiſt <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quotidie enim demitur aliqua pars vitae: &amp; tunc quoque cum creſcimus, vita de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcit.</hi> We dye daily, euery day paſſes away a part of our life; and while wee are yet waxing, does our life decreaſe.<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Hunc ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum quem agimus diem, cum morte diuidimus:</hi> This very day that we now liue, doe we diuide with death.<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Heliodor. in Epitaph. Neſoliani.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc ipſum quod dicto, quod ſcribitur, quod relego, qnod emendo, de vita mea tollitur.</hi> As by the times of eating, ſleeping, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, playing: ſo by the inſtants of ſpeaking, reading, writing, our liues are leſſened. Yea (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) this houre, theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my preaching, and your hearing, are taken away from both our liues.</p>
            <p>We dye daily: our times dye daily, our actions dye daily, our perſons dye daily. Our times dye daily: the time paſt, is dead
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3138:9"/>to the time preſent; the time preſent, is dying to the time to come: yeſterday is dead to To-day, and To-day is dying to To-morrow. Our actions dye daily: what is done and paſt, is dead to what is now doing: and what is now doing, is dying to what hereafter muſt bee done. We neither remember what we haue done, nor conceiue what wee haue done, nor delight in what wee haue done: ſo daily dye our actions to our memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to our vnderſtandings, to our affections. Our perſons dye daily: our infancy dyes into childhood, our childhood into youth, our youth into man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, our manhood into old age, and our old age dyes into death. A man is in a continuall conſumption of himſelfe: His dayes ſpend him alſo, as hee ſpends his dayes Euery day one part or piece o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him languiſheth or periſheth, corrupteth, and is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3138:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3138:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3138:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>caſt away.<note place="margin">Seneca vt ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Non repente in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem incidimus, ſed minutatim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedimus.</hi> We dye by piece-meale, and not all at once. There is no day in which our ſpirits vaniſh not, our bloud cooles not, our moyſture dryes not, our ſtomack fayles not, our liuer corrupts not, our lungs conſume not, our bowels yearn not, our heart faints not, our head akes not: euery day, either ſome veine ſtops, ſome ſinew ſhrinkes, or ſome bone breakes: either is ſome skinne withered, ſome fleſh bruiſed, or ſome member decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Euery day more then other, either the eyes grow dimme of ſeeing, the eares dull of hearing, or elſe the palate vnſauory of taſting. Thus dye the parts by little and little, and thus is the whole dead at laſt. The Candle ſtill conſumes, from the time it firſt beginnes to burne: ſo wade the oyle and marrow of a mans life, from the time that he begins
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3138:11"/>to liue. Man is a Candle, that either conſumes himſelfe vpon the candleſticke of the world, or elſe ſweales away vnder the buſhell of his Mothers wombe. The houre-glaſſe runnes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, from the time it is turned. Man is an houre-glaſſe, but a running ſand, or mouing duſt. And as the ſand in the houre-glaſſe fals corne by corne, or mite by mite, till the heape bee runne out: ſo a man drops a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by little and little, till the whole lumpe be done. A Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller goes many dayes onward to his iourneyes end. Man is this Traueller, this life the way, and death the iourneyes end. And is it a ſtrange thing to dye, when our whole life is but the way to death?<note place="margin">Sen. ep. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tu non putabas te aliquando peruenturum ad id, ad quod ſemper ibas?</hi> Can we thinke not once to come to, what wee alwayes goe to? There is no way on earth without an end: the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3138:12"/>intricateſt labyrinth hath a way out at laſt. Wee goe towards death continually, how ſhould we but meet withall at laſt? Wee dye daily, how ſhould wee but once be dead?<note place="margin">Bern. ſer.</note> 
               <hi>Miſer homo, quare te omni hora non diſponis? cogita te iam mortuum, quem ſcis neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate moriturum.</hi> Wretched man then, who euer thou art, ſeeing thou dyeſt daily, why doſt thou not daily diſpoſe thy ſelfe for death? thinke thy ſelfe now dead, whom thou knoweſt needes muſt dye. Woe to vs wretches all! that ſo many of vs are ſo neare death, and yet put it ſo farre from vs: ſo neere it in the euent, and yet put it ſo farre from vs in the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Death is ready to take vs by the hand, in the naturall execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ere wee are willing to take death to heart by a chriſtian me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation. Wee goe toward the graue, with our faces backward: our feet are at poynt to fall into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3138:12"/>it, ere our eyes once looke vpon it. We many feele Death before we know Death: &amp; are brought wofully to hazard, or experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence it; ere we are drawne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider, and conceiue it, though we ſee it dayly in others; yet can we not be led to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it in our ſelues: hereof haue we daily warning;<note place="margin">Eucher: epiſt: Paraen.</note> yet will we make it vnawares. <hi>Nihil ita quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie homines vt mortem, vident; nihil ita obliuiſcuntur vt mortem.</hi> Men daily behould nothing more then Death, and yet then Death, they forget, they neglect nothing more. But to bring you (beloued) to the knowledge, the conſideration &amp; remembrance of Death; I haue taken this text <hi>(O Death, where is thy ſting)</hi> both to inſtruct you concerning it; as alſo to incourage you againſt it. Where note firſt an Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſecondly an Interrogation: an Appellation, or Death ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned; <hi>O Death!</hi> an Intero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3138:13"/>or Death dared; <hi>Where is thy ſting?</hi> Where I haue 1. Something to ſay to Death, for your inſtruction; <hi>O Death!</hi> 2. One thing to aske of Death, for your incouragement; <hi>Where is thy ſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. The Appellation, or Death ſummoned; where I am to ſay ſomething to Death, for your inſtruction: <hi>O Death!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death!</hi> what art thou? a Chimaera, a Fable, a Buggebeare a Dreame, a Shadow, a nothing. O Death, thou art a ſtrange thing conſider: Thou art none of Gods Creature:<note place="margin">Wiſedom. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>God made not Death, neither hath he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the deſtruction of the liuing.</hi> God is the God of our being, he delights not in our deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Death was intended not for vs, but for our Sinne: therefore are we mortall, that ſinne might not bee immortall: Wee muſt therefore dye, once, that it might not alwayes liue.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3138:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>O Death,</hi> what doſt thou? thou diſſolueſt the rareſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of Heauen and Earth; thou diſtinguiſheſt betwixt our Spirit, and our Clay; Body and Soule thou ſeparateſt, ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per art thou then any two edged ſword, and entreſt to the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſunder of the Soule and Spirit, thou euen diuideſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the marrow and the bone. Thou makeſt our Duſt returne to the Earth, whence it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and our Spirit to God that gaue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh Death!</hi> thou makeſt our Spirit vaniſh, our Breath ſtop, our blood coole, our colour change, our Beauty fade, our Strength fall,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.</note> Thou makeſt the keepers of the houſe (our hands) to tremble, and the ſtrong men (our feet) to bow themſelues: Thou makeſt the grinders (our Teeth) to ceaſe, and them that looke out of the windowes (our Eyes) to waxe darke: Thou
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3138:14"/>ſhutteſt the Doores of our lippes and ſtoppeſt our windpipes, the Daughters of our ſinging: Thou cutteſt ſhort the ſiluer cord of Marrow; and breakeſt the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Ewer of our Brainpanne: Thou breakeſt the Pitcher of our veines, at the Well of our Liuer; at the Ceſterne of our Heart, there breakeſt thou the wheele of our Head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> thou art doomed to vs all. <hi>It is appointed for all men once to dye.</hi> We all walke this one way, all tread this one path; we muſt all ſleepe, our laſt ſleepe; and that darke night of Death, will once ouertake vs all, <hi>Patres noſtri praeterierunt, nos abimus, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteri ſequuntur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eucher: Paraen.</note> Our Fathers are dead, our Friends are dead, and our ſelues alſo muſt dye. Some are gone before vs, ſome accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany vs and ſome come after vs, like waue after waue are we daſht againſt the hard and cold ſtone Death, <hi>Serius aut citius, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3138:14"/>proper ammad vnaus.</hi> And thus ſoone, or late we dye all at laſt. We are borne, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to dye: We therefore put on the Garment of our Body, to put it off. and at firſt take vp the load of Nature, to lay it dowen at laſt. Death is Natures Law; and to dye, is but to pay Natures Tribute. It is as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for vs to liue, and dye; as for to wake, and ſleepe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death,</hi> Thou art certainely comming, yet vncertaine is it when thou wilt come. <hi>Nil cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius morte, at hora mortis incertius nihil.</hi> Nothing more certaine then Death; but then the houre of Death, nothing more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine;<note place="margin">Matth. 24.36.</note> 
               <hi>Of that day, and houre knoweth no man.</hi> That is, of the day of Iudgement, &amp; the houre of Death. Death comes as a Thiefe in the night, both ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, and violently: it takes vs, one vpon the houſe top, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Field; one working
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3138:15"/>in the Vine-yard, another grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the Mill: one vpon the houſe top of honours, another in the field of Pleaſures; one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Vineyard of a Chriſtian Calling, another grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the Mill of worldly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.12.</note> 
               <hi>A man knoweth not his time,</hi> that is, the time of his death. God will not tell vs the time, when Death ſhal come vpon vs; becauſe hee would haue vs thinke it neuer but neere vs: He will not let vs know our laſt day; becauſe he would haue vs ſuſpect and expect euery day to be our laſt. <hi>Latet vltimus dies vt obſeruentur omnes dies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug de diſcipl: Chriſtiana.</note> This one houre, the houre of Death is hidden from vs; that all the houres of our life might the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be obſerued by vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death,</hi> thou art impartiall, and indifferent to all. <hi>Pauperam tabernas, regumque turres:</hi> thou knockeſt equally at the Pallace, as the Cottage doore: thou like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3138:15"/>a Kings ſcull to a Beggers, and makeſt no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene their duſt. Neither haſt thou pitty vpon the Poore, nor reſpect vnto the Rich; neither ſcorneſt thou the fooliſh, nor doſt thou reuerence the wiſe:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>How dyeth the wiſeman? as doth the Foole.</hi> The oldman, thou long threatneſt; the yong man, thou ſoone betrayeſt, Neither ſpareſt thou for Age, Sexe, Degrees, nor Gifts. No Power of ours can forbid thee; no Diligence auoyd thee; no teares moue thee; Price hire thee; no art, or Eloquence perſwade thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death,</hi> thou art manifold: thou commeſt to vs in ſundry hues and ſhapes. Thou approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt pale, and leane, to the old man; bloody, &amp; boyſterous, to the yong man; blacke as hell, to the bad man, and but vgly, vnto euery man. Thou comeſt to vs, ſometimes in Mens hands, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Beaſtes mouthes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3138:16"/>in a flame of fire, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a waue of water, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a blaſt of wind; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the ſlipping of a foote ſomtimes in the faling of a ſtone Thou comeſt to vs, ſometimes in our cloaths, and ſometimes in our Meate and Drinke. We dye diuerſly: Some by warre, ſome in Peace; ſome by Sea, ſome by land; ſome in the Field, ſome on our Beds; ſome by our own violence, or Intemperance ſome by a ſudden wound, and ſome by a languiſhing diſeaſe <hi>Mille modis lethi miſeres mors vnafatigat.</hi> And thus, by a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand wayes of dying, one Death deſtroyes vs all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death, how bitter is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccluſ. 41.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>to a man that liue that reſt in his poſſeſſions, &amp;c. O Death, how acceptable is thy iudgement vnto the needfull, &amp;c.</hi> O Death thou art a ſhadow in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thou fleeſt thoſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee; and followeſt thoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3138:16"/>that flee thee, <hi>Mors optata re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit; at cum triſtis erit, praecipi. tata venit.</hi> Thou haſtneſt then, when we wiſh to eſchue thee; then delayeſt thou, when we ſeeke to imbrace thee. Death is the rich mans Feare; and the poore mans Deſire: Often cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon, in Aduerſity; neuer thought vpon in proſperity. In proſperity, we complaine, and cry with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.</note> to haue it further added into our dayes: But in aduerſity, we can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent euery one to wiſh with <hi>Elijah; It is enough now O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 19.4.</note> 
               <hi>take away my Soule, for I am no better then my Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O Death!</hi> How fearefull a thing art thou to fleſh and blood? How abhor we, to haue the graue, forour houſe; to make our bed in darkeneſſe; to ſay to Corruption, thou art my Father; and to the Worme, thou art my Siſter, and my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? How doe we hate to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3138:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3138:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3138:18"/>ſerpents, and wormes; to be ſeparated from our ſelues; to be returned to our duſt? how does Death terrifie vs, not onely in our owne experience, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers example? In others Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; ſo oft as we ſee or heare an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is dead; it troubles vs to thinke, that wee alſo muſt dye. For our owne experience; how are we then agaſt, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either what we muſt be or whither we muſt goe? Wee are afraid to dye, euen we, who haue good hope after Death: Euen we that looke for an houſe not made with hands; are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding loath to leaue this houſe of clay: we that haue the promiſe of a Kingdome, are but vnwilling to forgoe our Priſon: There is a Feare in vs, to be diſſolued; notwithſtanding our Deſire to be with Chriſt: and we many irke to vndergoe the Paſſage, that euen reioyce to approach to the Home.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3138:18"/> 2 An interrogation, or death dared, where I am to aske this one thing of death, for your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement: <hi>where is thy ſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not onely this I am now to aske of death but that I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid to death, (truely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered) ſerues to incourage vs againſt death. Death is a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ad pop. hom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> but a very Bug-beare: and are we (like children) afraid of Hobgoblings onely? death is a nothing, and are wee afraid of we know not what? Death ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates betwixt ſoule and body; why feare wee ſo it ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue vs, when wee ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce rather, that it cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs? Feare wee what may ſeparate vs from our ſelues? ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imbrace we, what will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey vs to Chriſt. Death is deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to vs all, and why feare we, what we cannot eſchew? Our willingneſe to dye, is the onely way to preuent the neceſſity of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3138:19"/>death.<note place="margin">Chryſ in Mat. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Offeramus Deopro munere, quod debito teneamur reddere.</hi> Let vs therefore offer God our liues, as a free gift, which hee will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe require as a due debt. Deaths comming is vncertaine, and ſhall any vncertaine thing cauſe in vs a certaine feare? <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certum eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. ep <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quo te loco mors expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctet; itaque tu illam omni loco ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecta.</hi> Rather, ſeeing it is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, at what time, or in what place death will ouertake vs; let vs therefore bee ſure to expect death at all times, and in euery place. Death is equall and impartiall to all; this alſo ſhould make vs leſſe afraid of death.<note place="margin">Sen ep. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quis queri poteſt, in ea conditione ſe eſſe, in qua nemo non eſt?</hi> Who can complaine, when himſelfe is but in ſuch a caſe or conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in which none are not? Who lookes that ſhee ſhould ſpare any, that knowes her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different to all? When the like ruine is threatned to an whole
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3138:19"/>world, who expects that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould eſcape alone? Some comfort againſt the cruelty of death, is her equality. There are diuers wayes of dying, and ſhould that make vs afraid of death? No matter how we dye, ſeeing the moſt is but to be dead. <hi>Non multum curandum eſt eis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ciu. Dei.</note> 
               <hi>qui neceſſario merituri ſunt, quid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidet, vt moriantur; ſed moriendo, quo ire cogantur.</hi> Since wee muſt dye, it skilleth not how we dye, but whether we muſt goe after death. Laſtly, death is a thing fearefull to fleſh and bloud; yet ſhould not all this make vs afraid of death. For it is not death, but the feare of death, that is ſo fearefull. This feare fulneſſe is rather from our owne ignorance, then according to the nature of the thing, <note place="margin">Chryſ. ad pop. hom. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: did we but know death, wee would not ſo feare death. The feare of death
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3138:20"/>is the puniſhment of our igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and negligence, which make vs apprehend things, as new and ſtrange things, which otherwiſe are neither ſtrange, nor new. The onely way then to make death not ſo fearefull to vs, is (by a daily meditation thereof) to make it more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar; to acquaint our ſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, before the comming, that we may leſſe feare it when it comes. And thus, firſt learning not to feare death, at laſt come wee to dare death; <hi>O death! where is thy ſting?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Death is not yet deſtroyed, for <hi>the laſt enemy that ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed is death;</hi> but death is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready diſarmed; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> The Text is an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: The Captaines ſong of victory, as alſo the Souldiers ſong of deliuery. The words are of a mighty Conquerour, braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſulting ouer a baſe and wretched enemy. And who is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3138:20"/>this conquerour of death, but <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> the Lord of life? It was hee, ſpake in the Prophets words, <hi>O death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>I will bee thy death;</hi> and in his power, ſpeakes the Apoſtle here, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quia in electis fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus occidit mortem, mors mortis extitit.</hi> Chriſt did once ſubdue death for vs; <hi>O death, I will be thy death;</hi> and we may now deride death in Chriſt, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? Olim morti noſtrae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>8.</hi> paſſion.</note> 
               <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuae potentiam minabatur.</hi> Chriſt once threatned his death to our death, <hi>O death, I will be thy death;</hi> wherefore wee now may glory in the vertue of his death, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the malice of our owne, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt ouercame death by dying: nay, through death, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed be, not death onely, but him alſo that had the power of death, the Deuill.<note place="margin">Heb. 7.14.</note> Our Captaine both beate our enemy at her owne weapon, and caught the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3138:21"/>Hunter in his owne ſnare. Hee but yeelded to death, to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage againſt her: yea, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dyed the life, that death might no longer liue.<note place="margin">Chryſ. in Math. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Non Chriſtum mortuum in morte credimus, ſed mortem mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuam in Chriſto.</hi> Wee doe not thinke that Chriſt is dead in death, but beleeue that death is dead in Chriſt. Death, that gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Whale durſt deuoure Chriſt, our <hi>Ionas,</hi> (who was therefore caſt forth into the ſea of the world, that ſo the ſtormes and tempeſts of the deuill, and ſinne, might ceaſe) but hee was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued aliue in the Fiſhes belly (the belly of hell, the iawes of death) to preach repentance to the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue</hi> of the Church. This ſame Whale ſwallowed the baite of Chriſts humanity, but the hook of his diuinity intangled her, and made her vomit vp her bowels,<note place="margin">Hieron. lib. <hi>1.</hi> ep. ad Heliodor.</note> together with the baite. <hi>Deuoraſti, &amp; deuorata es.</hi> Death
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3138:21"/>thought to haue ſwallowed Chriſt downe in obſcurity, and ſo death her ſelfe was ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp in victory. Death, that Serpent, was bold to ſting Chriſt; but he made her loſe her ſting for her labour. His huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity could but receiue her ſting, of which his Diety did depriue her. So that wee may well aske her in him: <hi>O death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.56. Ioh. 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>where is thy ſting? The ſting of death is ſinne: Chriſt, the Lamb of God, hath taken away the ſins of the world.</hi> In <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> therefore may we ſecurely ſay: <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob</hi> askt of man, <hi>Man dyeth, and where is he?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 14.10.</note> but wee may aske as much of death: Man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and where is death? yea, wee may aske concerning the worſt of death, deaths ſting; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? Iacob</hi> thus bewailed the death of <hi>Ioſeph, Ioſeph</hi> is dead <hi>Ioſeph</hi> is not.<note place="margin">Gen. 42.</note> And <hi>Rachel</hi> wept for her children, and would not bee comforted,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3138:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3138:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3138:23"/>becauſe they were not.<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> Becauſe death was there, they thought their children to bee no where. But now, death does but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey vs where we ſhould be, and death it ſelfe is no where. <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> Death is quite vndone ſince the Croſſe of Chriſt. When death entred firſt into the world,<note place="margin">Exod. 15.</note> it was like the waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> exceeding bitter: but ſince the Tree of the Croſſe of Chriſt, was caſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, it is now ſeaſoned and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs. Wee might once cry out with the children of the Prophets:<note place="margin">2 King. 4.</note> death is in the pot, death is in the pot: But ſince, Chriſt hath ſaid, This Cup is the new Teſtament in my bloud: we may now ſay with the Saints of God; The Cup of Saluation, Saluation is in the Cup. There is now no more death, ſince the Lord of life. <hi>Vita cius inſtruxit noſtram, mors deſtruxit noſtram.</hi> His life hath inſtructed our life,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3138:23"/>his death, deſtroyed our death; his life quickened ours, his death ſweetned ours. his life tooke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way death from our life; his death, gaue life to our death.</p>
            <p>The Text askes not this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; O death, what is thy ſting? yet doe the words following make anſwere to ſuch a queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>The ſting of death is ſinne.</hi> (Death belike is not the ſting of ſinne, but ſinne the ſting of death: <hi>peccato enim morimur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anſelm. in l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>non morte peccamus;</hi> Sith we d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, by ſinning, but ſinne not by dying.) And as the words following anſwere to a queſtion, they aske not; So my Text askes a queſtion, to which it anſweres not; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> It does not tell you where it is, to tell you, it is no where. Death hath now no ſting. <hi>I am non eſt ſtimulus, ſed ſibilus, immo iubilus.</hi> Reioyce all, and be glad; This Serpent may hiſſe at vs, this Bee may buzze about vs, but now
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3138:24"/>can neither pricke nor ſting. The ſting of death is gone; there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines but the name of death; nay, not the name of death to them that are in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus. Mors piorum, non mors dicenda, &amp;c.</hi> The death of the godly is not to bee called a death, but a ſleepe, a reſting from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a deliuery from their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a laying downe their loade, a flitting to their home. Death hath loſt her ſting. Death is now no puniſhment, but a paſſage; not ſo much an end of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, as an entrance to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; not a deſtruction now, but a diſſolution, ſeparating body and ſoule for a time, that ſo both may be conioyned with Chriſt to eternity.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I askt this one thing of death, <hi>O death; where is thy ſting?</hi> Now let me aske this one thing of you, why are you ſo deſperately and forlornely afraid of death, hauing heard
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3138:24"/>and knowne how death hath loſt her ſting? Oh ſaithleſſe man, and faint hearted! Why trembleſt thou now to incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with thy laſt enemy, ſince her weapon is taken from her? Shrinkeſt thou ſo at the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Serpent, when thou knoweſt her poyſon and ſting are both away? Oh faithleſſe, and faint-hearted, to be ſo afraid of a ſhadow? Ah wretches! why feare wee death ſo deſperately; that are not loſt, but ſent before; whom death vtterly deſtroyes not, but eternity once receiues? It is for them to feare death ſo deſperately, that paſſe from one death to another; namely, from a death of the body once on earth, to the death of body and ſoule in hell for euer. It is for them ſo forlornely to feare a temporall death, that are either ignorant, or deſperate of eternall life. It is for them ſo to feare their flittings, that goe from
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3138:25"/>their priſon, to the place of their execution. But as for vs that are in <hi>Christ Ieſus,</hi> wee paſſe from a Priſon, to a Palace; from a Dunghill, to a Throne, from a crazy and wretched Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, to a certaine and bleſſed home.<note place="margin">Cypr. de mortal.</note> 
               <hi>Eius eſt mortem timere, qui non vult ad Chriſtumire.</hi> It is for them to feare to be diſſolued, that hope not to be with Chriſt. A forlorne feare of death, is but a deſpaire of life after death. Men had rather ſuffer a great deale of paine, and liue, then dye but with a little paine: the which betokens, that it is ſomething after death, that is ſo fearefull, and not death it ſelfe. Let them then deſire to linger in the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this preſent life, that ſo but delay awhile the torments of the life to come. But as for vs that are in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our ſtormes and ſhipwracks, why feare wee to arriue at our Hauen? Hauing fought a good
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3138:25"/>fight, and finiſhed our courſe, why doubt we to goe and haue our crowne? hauing runne our race, why are we ſo loath to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine our price? Why ſhould we feare the threatnings of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death, that may reioyce in the promiſes of eternall life?<note place="margin">Rom. 14.8</note> 
               <hi>Whether we liue, wee liue vnto the Lord, whether we dye, we dye vnto the Lord: therefore whether wee liue or dye, we are the Lords:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let vs bee ſo diſſolute, and prophane of life, as therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to liue, nor ſo ignorant and negligent of death, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore afraid to dye. But at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of our ſeuerall flittings, ſay euery one, as a dying Saint; <hi>Egredere, quid times?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron in vita Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion.</note> 
               <hi>egredere anima mea, &amp;c.</hi> Goe forth my ſoule! why feareſt thou? goe forth. Learne each ſoule to ſay at the laſt paſſage of his pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage: what though I dye. I know my Redeemer liueth; though I be diſſolued from my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3138:26"/>ſelfe, yet ſhall I bee conioyned with Chriſt. Lye then downe (my body!) and returne vnto thy duſt; mount thou aloft (my ſoule!) and meet thy Sauiour in the ayre; my body may be but wormes-meate for a while, my ſoule (I am aſſured) ſhall be an Angels fellow for euer.</p>
            <p>I haue done with my Text as concerning you, before whom it hath beene vttered. I am now onely to apply it to this honourable party, for whom it was intended. This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable party, your doletull ſpectacle, and my Texts vntime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occaſion; This honourable party, our Maſter, Father, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; this honourable party, whoſe honour, for his perſon, now lyes in the duſt; for his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, Lord let it long, and much, both continue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</p>
            <p>The bleſſed Saints of God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3138:26"/>learne many good leſſons in their liues, which they both teach, and vſe at their death. Concerning this Saint now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, wee that heard, can wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, how well he had learnt to adapt the prayers and ſayings of the faithfull, and former Saints, to his owne, and inſtant neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.<note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> He ſang with <hi>Simeon, Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſeruant depart in peace.</hi> Hee prayed with Saint <hi>Paul, deſiring to be diſſolued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and to be with Chriſt.</hi> Yea, ſaid hee, with both the lingring and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saints, <hi>How long Lord, how long? Euen ſo come Lord Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 6. Reu. 22.</note> 
               <hi>come quickly.</hi> One of theſe ſweet ſayings of his owne application, had giuen me my Text to treat of, ſaue that I conſidered, this Text that I haue choſen, did as much as intimate them all. For, to pray to depart, to deſire to be diſſolued, to call for the haſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to complaine of the deferring; What other is all
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3138:27"/>this, but as in my Text, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſummon death, <hi>O death!</hi> and ſtou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to daredeath, <hi>where is thy ſting?</hi> Hee mentioned the departing, hee expected the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing, but he neuer feared the ſtinging. Hee knew hee ſhould not be loſt, he ſhould but depart; therefore ſayes he, <hi>Lord, now let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thou thy ſeruant depart, &amp;c.</hi> He knew well, death could but diſſolue him, it could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him; he therefore ſaid, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolued, &amp;c.</hi> And this is no more, then as if hee had demanded of death here in defiance; <hi>O death, where is thy ſting?</hi> As hee had thus ſaid; O death, thou art death indeede, and thou mayeſt diſſolue mee; but where is thy ſting? Sting haſt thou none, and therefore thou canſt not deſtroy me.</p>
            <p>It hath beene alwayes the Churches vſe, not onely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, but commend the liues of the Faithfull, being dead, that ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3138:27"/>the liuing might come to know their conuerſation, and bee brought to follow their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Both for our information, and imitation of this Saint de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed; I could gladly, (as I might iuſtly) inlarg my ſelfe to a volume of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is prayſe. I flatter him not to ſay the beſt I can of him, that is now better then I can tell how to ſay. To p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayſe a good man after his death, is not to flatter him, but to prayſe God for him: beſides, a dead mans commendation, is the liuings admonition. Then wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould we forget, whom we ought to imitate? Why ſhould his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues dye with him, before men on earth? whoſe graces are gone before him, and liue before the face of Chriſtin heauen. Let vs yet therefore ſpeake of him, when wee cannot now ſpeake with him. Let vs haue him now in our mindes, while he is now no more before our eyes: hauing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3138:28"/>now loſt his preſence, let vs inioy him yet in his remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
            <p>The life of our Honourable and deare Brother departed, muſt I remember vnto you, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the two-fold ſtate of life; his proſperity, his aduerſity; and in them both, I commend vnto you his Chriſtianity. Hee is worthy the conſideration in either ſtate: In as much as hee dranke deepe of a mixed Cup; both had he his ſhare of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-combe, and withall, was vineger and gall made his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to drinke: as a large talent was giuen him, ſo an heauy load was layd vpon him. God won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully both bleſſed, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted him, becauſe in both (as himſelfe both found and ſaid) God would try him to the full. And indeede, neither ſtate did more then exerciſe, and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him: for, neither did the height of his proſperity, puff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3138:28"/>him vp, nor could the depth of his aduerſity depreſſe him. In his proſperity I neuer heard but that he was iuſt, and temperate. This I can ſay, hee was both humble and thankefull in his affliction.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For his proſperity in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and there to beginne with him as ſoone as he began to proſper. He was a man (as it is well knowne) worſhipfully borne, religiouſly educated, wiſely inſtructed, honorably promoted; A man happy in a loyall wife, ioyfull in vertuous children, proſperous in worldly wealth. Nor were his proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo commendable, but for his Piety, and charity. For his Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he ſerued his God, hee reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced the Church, hee heard the word, he beleeued the truth, he endeauoured the good; His ſighs and teares, could witneſſe his tender heartedneſſe; ſo his prayers, and meditations, his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3138:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3138:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3138:30"/>heauenly mindedneſſe. For his Charity, it is well noted, where euer he had any thing to dee, the firſt thing he did, was alwaies to doe good. Beſides his oft, and priuate almes, his light moreouer ſhines in publique, and both in City, and country, men may ſee his good workes. Were I (for memory, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſake) to catel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gue, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord his works, I could declare when, how, where, hee ſpared neither for hundreds, nor for thouſands, to doe good. But ſuch a thing I rather thinke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy a wide worlds eye, then but only a ſmall peoples care. What he hath beſtowed to pious and charitable vſes amount to more then 11000. pounds. And this the ſeuerall places endowed can truely witneſſe, and Parties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſitted ſhall thankfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. Both liuing and dying was he largely and variouſly benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. As for the moſt things of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3138:30"/>common vſe, and neede, theſe were the obiects of his liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Hale, Hoſpitals, Priſons, Schooles, Colledges, and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; of ſome was he ſole Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to ſome a free Benefactour I might (not amiſſe) call him a man of good workes. Hee was food to the hungry, a garment to the naked, comfort to the ſicke, a reliefe vnto the priſoner, and an harbour euen to the ſtranger: For, beſides thoſe of his acquaintance, many one had cauſe to bleſſe him, that ſcarce euer ſaw his face. One thing I may not here omit, that when he had done much good for many, hee further demanded of vs, Who was there would haue him doe any thing for them? And when he had freely and orderly giuen the laſt he gaue, hee yet ask<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, what elſe was for him to doe? Though his good deeds were many and munificent, yet ſuch words ſhewed a minde,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3138:31"/>beyond his deeds; that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he had done well, and ſufficient, yet was he not ſatisfied with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Touching his aduerſity; his heauenly Father, as hee had for a long time imbraced this his Sonne, in the armes of his bleſſings: ſo did his heauy hand ſcourge him ſore, now that hee receiued him. Hee ſo cheriſhed him, as not to let him eſcape the whip. And all to tell him, he could not be ſo happy here, as not to be miſerable, and muſt be miſerable a while, to be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for euer, During the time of his ſinkneſſe, his ſufferings were both tedious and extreame, ſo that (comparing h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his yeares) we won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred he could be ſo mightily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, and yet ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubſiſt in his afflictions. Both were his paines great, and groanes many, and (for many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together) his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3138:31"/>and ſleepe (in compariſon) ſmall, or none. His Bed was but as his Racke; the place of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall refreſhment, as an engine of extreame torment. Nor was any time ſo reſtleſſe to him, as the common time of reſt. For all which, he was neuer heard to charge God fooliſhly, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, in his wholeſome Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, his holy Confeſſions, his hearty Inuocations; ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued hee his breath to the laſt. All thoſe godly and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſayings that proceeded from him, ſhould I now vtter them in particular, I ſuppoſe it would bee another Sermon to recite them. Laſtly, hauing both appoynted, and perfected his whole bequeſts, and ſo ſet his houſe in order, and now quite renounced the world, ſetting himſelfe (as he ſaid) to preſent his ſoule before God in Chriſt: after a long and bitter agony, and now towards the doomed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3138:32"/>and expected moment of this peaceable paſſage: while our hearts groaned, and eyes diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their deuotions his ſoule beganne already to be rauiſhed in her heauenly viſions, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed contemplations: and ſo, he cheerefully flitting from vs, left vs ſadly looking on.</p>
            <p>To inſiſt long vpon the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the Dead, is (in ſome caſe) to adde vnto the ſorrowes of the liuing: For, to heare his goodneſſe prayſed, cannot but this way grieue vs, namely, in that wee haue loſt ſo great a good. We haue loſt him, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> haue loſt him; nor indeed is he loſt, but to vs. We haue ſome loſt a Lord, ſome loſt a Friend, ſome loſt a Magiſtrate, ſome loſt a Maſter, ſome loſt a Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, ſome loſt a Patron, one loſt a Husband, ſome loſt a Father, and (to mine owne particular) next a Father, his loſſe was mine. To reckon ſo manifold
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3138:32"/>a loſſe, my Teares begin to ſtop my ſpeech; and bid me bewaile it rather in ſobbes, then words. But I refraine the rather to let looſe mine owne paſſion at this time and place; conſidering how vnfitting he is to comfort others, whoſe owne ſorrowes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome himſelfe. It is not for me now to ſhew ſorrow in my face, that am now to ſpeake comfort to your heatts.</p>
            <p>Comfort we our ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (Brethren) in the Lord, in whom (wee beleeue) this our Brother doth now reioyce. Let vs be content to loſe him whom it hath pleaſed God to gaine: How iuſtly might he take him away from vs, that euen gaue him to himſelfe? Letvs not only bewaile that we want him, but reioyce rather, that once we had him, He is dead, neither the firſt, nor laſt: we muſt follow after, whither he is but gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Neither was he violently
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3138:33"/>nor vntimely ſnatcht away from <hi>vs,</hi> but he ſlept peaceably, and dyed in a good age. Let it not then ſo afflict vs, to thinke how wee may miſſe him here on earth, as reioyce vs to expect how we muſt meet him in the Ayre, at the laſt comming of the Lord <hi>Ieſus.</hi> To which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thine (Lord <hi>Ieſu</hi>) not only haſten, but prepare: that when thou ſhalt deſcend from Heauen with a ſhout, with the voyce of the Archangell, and the Trumpe of God; we which ſhall then liue and remaine, may be caught vp with them (euen this our Brother, and all thine holy Saints and Angels) in the clouds; and ſo be, &amp; be bleſt with thee our onely Lord and Sauiour, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="catalogue_of_deeds">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:33"/>
            <head>A iuſt and neceſſary Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of ſuch Noble and Charitable Deeds, as haue beene done by the late Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>Baptiſt</hi> Lord <hi>Hickes,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Campden,</hi> as well in his Life, as at his Death: recorded to the glory of God, his own Honour, and others good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</head>
            <div type="deeds">
               <head>Good deeds done to the Towne of <hi>Campden,</hi> in the County of <hi>Glouceſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>HEe built an Almeſ-houſe or Hoſpitall for <hi>6.</hi> poore men, and <hi>6.</hi> poore women, coſt <hi>1000. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Since the yeare of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the ſaid Almeſ-houſe, <hi>ſc. 1612.</hi> Hee hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb facs="tcp:3138:34"/>the ſaid <hi>12.</hi> poore people, wachely maintenance, to the value of <hi>1300. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And now at his death, hee hath ſetled <hi>140. l. per annum</hi> for euer vpon the ſaid Almeſ-houſe, allowing each of the ſaid poore Priſoners <hi>3. s. 4. d.</hi> week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yeerely a Gowne, a Hat, and a Tunne of Coales. <hi>per annum. 140. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hee built a commodious Market-houſe in the ſaid Towne, coſt <hi>90. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>By his laſt Will, hee gaue to the ſaid Towne for the ſetting of the poore to worke, a ſtocke of <hi>500. l.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="deeds">
               <head>To the Church of <hi>Campden.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>He gaue a Bell, coſt <hi>66. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Made a Pulpit, gaue a Cloath and Cuſhion, coſt <hi>22. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Built a Gallery, coſt <hi>8. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3138:34"/>
                  <item>Made a Window, coſt <hi>13. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gaue a braſſe Falcon, coſt <hi>26. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Gaue two Comunion Cups, coſt <hi>21. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Built the roofe of the Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and new leaded it, coſt <hi>200 l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Herepaired the Chappell by the ſaid Chauncell, ſupplyed, and new caſt the Leades, coſt <hi>20. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He walled the Church-yard round, coſt <hi>150. l.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="deeds">
               <head>Within the County of <hi>Middleſex.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>Hee built a Seſsions Houſe for the Iuſtices of Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, to keepe their Seſsions in, coſt <hi>600. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He repaired, and adorned the Chappell of <hi>Hamſtead,</hi> coſt <hi>76. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3138:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>He ſet vp a Window in the Chauncell of <hi>Kenſington,</hi> and beautified it, coſt <hi>30. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hee hath giuen by his laſt Will to the ſaid Towne of <hi>Kenſington,</hi> to bee imployed for the benefit of the poore, the ſumme of <hi>200. l.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="deeds">
               <head>In the City of <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>Hee hath giuen by his laſt Will to S. <hi>Bartholomewes</hi> Hoſpitall, <hi>100. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. <hi>50. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>To <hi>New-Gate, Lud-Gate,</hi> and the two <hi>Counters, 40. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hee erected a Window in S. <hi>Laurence</hi> Church in the old <hi>Iewry,</hi> and gaue a Pulpit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th and Cuſhion, coſt <hi>30. l.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="gifts">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:35"/>
               <head>Impropriations purchaſed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vpon the Church.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>One in <hi>Pembrokeſhire,</hi> to be giuen to the Towne of <hi>Tewkesbury</hi> in <hi>Glouceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> whereof one moity to the Preacher, the other to the poore, coſt <hi>460. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Another in <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereof one moity to bee giuen toward the maintenance of an able Preacher in <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead,</hi> the other to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Schoole in <hi>London,</hi> towards the maintenance of certaine Schollers in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> coſt <hi>760 l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>One in the <hi>Biſhopricke</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> to bee beſtowed on ſuch Churches as ſhall haue moſt need thereof, according to the diſcretion of his Superui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, coſt <hi>366. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3138:36"/>
                  <item>Another in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> to bee beſtowed likewiſe, coſt <hi>760. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Certaine Chauntery Lands alſo in <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> coſt <hi>240. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Hee hath alſo giuen to two Miniſters to be choſen out of <hi>Ieſus Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> to ſerue in their ſeuerall places, <hi>40. l.</hi> a peece <hi>per annum, 80. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He hath bequeathed Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to ſeuerall Miniſters, the ſumme of <hi>140. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He hath giuen to <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. A. E.</hi> during his life, <hi>per annum, 100. l.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>He hath giuen amongſt his houſe-hold ſeruants <hi>300. l.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <div type="elegy">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:36"/>
               <head>An Elegie.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>If ſorrowes ſilent be; I ſhould bewray</l>
                  <l>An eaſineſſe, that would my ſorrow ſay.</l>
                  <l>But time is, and affection too affords,</l>
                  <l>To breathe from ſighes awhile, and breathe forth words.</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould I be cloſe niggard of my griefe?</l>
                  <l>Sith to impart it, is to finde reliefe.</l>
                  <l>I waile the loſſe of one; like Lot of all</l>
                  <l>Is to be wail'd, and fear'd in generall.</l>
                  <l>Alwayes the greater loſſe, the griefe the more:</l>
                  <l>While I applaud then, I muſt needs deplore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Bounties free hand, ah Bounty now lies bound!</l>
                  <l>Amities deare heart, hath felt a deadly wound.</l>
                  <l>Pieties pure ſoule, farre flitted is from hence:</l>
                  <l>Truths ſimple tongue, is buried in ſilence.</l>
                  <l>Iuſtice impartiall Eye, is ſhut vp faſt:</l>
                  <l>Sincerities bright countenance, defac't.</l>
                  <l>Temperance ſober palate, pal'd and cloy'd:</l>
                  <l>Chaſtities vnpolluted body, ſtroyd.</l>
                  <l>Attentions faithfull eare, hard ſtopt with earth:</l>
                  <l>Memories ſound braine minds now another birth.</l>
                  <l>Patience meeke ſpirit, humbled to the duſt:</l>
                  <l>Deuotions zealous Saint, raignes with the iuſt.</l>
                  <l>Experience long dayes and good, are gone:</l>
                  <l>Nobility is layd in graue alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Can ſo great loſſe in ſilence now be borne?</l>
                  <l>Or can I ſay, I miſſe him; and not mourne?</l>
                  <l>I hate to count, and not condole the loſſe</l>
                  <l>Of good men: none but bad men ſlight ſuch croſſe:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3138:37"/>
                  <l>And ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>w their teeth, cauſe others wet their eyes,</l>
                  <l>For loſſe of Saints; which they nor are, nor prize.</l>
                  <l>Once priz'd I one, who ſo prize-worthy was;</l>
                  <l>I daily learne to prize him by his loſſe.</l>
                  <l>I'le waile a priuate want; feare th' common dearth</l>
                  <l>Of goodneſſe; ſince good men ſo leaue the earth.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="epitaph">
               <head>An Epitaph.</head>
               <l>Reader know, who ere thou be;</l>
               <l>Here lyes Faith, Hope, and Charity:</l>
               <l>Faith true, Hope firme, Charity free;</l>
               <l>Baptiſt Lord Camdens were theſe three:</l>
               <l>Faith in God, Charity to brother,</l>
               <l>Hope for himſelfe; what ought he other?</l>
               <l>Faith is no more, Charity's crown'd;</l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> only Hope is vnder ground.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Baptiſtam Camdenum.</head>
               <l>Grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, dicit Camdenus hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> homi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> claru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ille Deo.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Baptiſtam deſunctum.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>buitferr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quandam Baptiſta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Baptiſta his noſter ſunere ſuccubuit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> non eſt, qui f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ere tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> nobis mors tulit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> caput.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>I. G.</bibl>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:37"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>If to be crown'd with honour of the Peeres:</l>
                  <l>If to be honour'd with a crowne of yeares:</l>
                  <l>If to haue wealth, and know the vſe of it,</l>
                  <l>To haue a ſolid and ingenious wit;</l>
                  <l>If goodly houſes, with good ſtore of land;</l>
                  <l>If an vnſpotted, and an open hand;</l>
                  <l>If ſtrength of minde, and vigor of the ſence,</l>
                  <l>A candid breſt, and a cleare conſcience:</l>
                  <l>A noble iſſue, and a noble race,</l>
                  <l>Endow'd with inward, and with outward grace:</l>
                  <l>If loue of friends, and friendſhip without ſtrife;</l>
                  <l>Obſervant children, and a faithfull wife,</l>
                  <l>If a religious and a loyall heart</l>
                  <l>May perfect bliffe to any man impart,</l>
                  <l>Then to Lord <hi>Campden;</hi> who in all this rowle</l>
                  <l>Had euery gift, in body or in ſoule:</l>
                  <l>His ſoule in heauen is a welcome gueſti:</l>
                  <l>Then let his bones in quiet ſilence reſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Memoriae ſacrae.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>Cùm tot faecundos Camdene p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>regeris annos;</l>
                  <l>At<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tuis largas cùm namerâris opes,</l>
                  <l>Cùm tibiſuccreſeant illuſtriſtirpe Nepotes;</l>
                  <l>Cùm mirâ celſas ſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>teris arte d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mes;</l>
                  <l>Cùm tibi partus honor, vict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paratus egenis:</l>
                  <l>Quid ſupereſt? vitra non ſuper eſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale.</salute>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <lg>
                  <l>Hieſius hic ſitus eſt; Campi qui gloria Deni:</l>
                  <l>Ternus, &amp; aeternus da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> meliora Deus.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>R. A.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:38"/>
               <head>Ad Avum defunctum.</head>
               <l>If good mens death be but a timely ſleepe,</l>
               <l>If man two childhoods hath, the firſt to keepe</l>
               <l>The firſt watch of his life, then that of age</l>
               <l>Which with the former ſtands in equipage</l>
               <l>Vſhering the ſecond better life, when you</l>
               <l>May in a moment all your yeares renew,</l>
               <l>And by the fruitfull priuiledge of death,</l>
               <l>Claime life againe more permanent then breath.</l>
               <l>Sith mans laſt breath to man doth life apply,</l>
               <l>Sith death's the childhood of eternity,</l>
               <l>Why weepe we? rather when you leaue this light</l>
               <l>We'le aske you bleſſing and bid you good night:</l>
               <l>Tis <hi>vale</hi> long enough now, for anon</l>
               <l>You'le be awake '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th reſurrection.</l>
               <l>Children muſt ſleepe then, ſo muſt age, and both</l>
               <l>Are rows'd from ſlumbring at their perfect growth:</l>
               <l>Sleepe then in earth thy cradle, ſecure lie,</l>
               <l>May Angels <hi>requiems</hi> be thy Iullaby,</l>
               <l>Till the laſt trumpe awake thee, and the faire</l>
               <l>Councel of Elders place thee in their chaire,</l>
               <l>When ioyntly with the quire of Angels bleſt</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt ſing <hi>Halle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iahs</hi> with the reſt.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Baptiſt Noel.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:38"/>
               <head>Proſopopoea Latinis Iambis.</head>
               <l>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icquid ſub Arcto, quicquid in gremio latet</l>
               <l>Thetidis, vel amplo conditur Ponti ſinu,</l>
               <l>Aut aeſtuantis febre perpetuâ canis</l>
               <l>Radians ocellus vidit inter fluctuum</l>
               <l>Ebullientes riuulos, vel anxius</l>
               <l>Quaerunt ſub vndis alacer Jndus, Aethiops,</l>
               <l>Mauruſue pelle nigricante Barbarus.</l>
               <l>Haec omnia domi nôſſe te (charum caput)</l>
               <l>Teſtantur Argonautae, &amp; abietum frequens</l>
               <l>Catena, malorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſiluae mobiles</l>
               <l>Ponti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nemora denſa, decumano mari</l>
               <l>Tot inſulas nutante fixas vertice</l>
               <l>Toties ſalutantia, iteratis nuncijs</l>
               <l>Dum tu Liburnarum reuiſens nauium</l>
               <l>Orbem ſtupentem, miſcuiſti Barbaris</l>
               <l>Gentem togatam, interfuiſti &amp; ſerijs.</l>
               <l>Mediante ſeruo Gangis in negotijs.</l>
               <l>At iſta menti praevolenti viltor</l>
               <l>Conditioſordet &amp; globiſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntia</l>
               <l>Exacta licet &amp; ampla terreni iacet</l>
               <l>Contempta, &amp; aequatur (quod explanat) ſolo.</l>
               <l>Coeleſtis ardor ſurgit ad coeleſtia,</l>
               <l>Nec ſufficit contractus orbis nauitae</l>
               <l>Terrae mariſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſcio, ſat ſemitae</l>
               <l>Rimae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cuiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> extimae, ſed altiùs</l>
               <l>Orbem ſupernum quaeris, illic for ſitan</l>
               <l>Coeleſtis Eridani fluentis nauigans</l>
               <l>Stellata in Argo coelum aquoſum tranſnatas.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>el forſan vndas atri adhuc tranans Stygis</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:39"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; inter viue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>Tantum hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>itam lice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vrnam carmin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taret <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tri dicat extremum vale</l>
               <l>Piet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſarc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nota</l>
               <l>Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> figet hoc Epitaphium.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Epitaphium.</head>
               <l>Tranſi viat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Et civit hic ſepult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt,</l>
               <l>At ſiſte gradum, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>idebis iſtum nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Redibit, hand m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rabit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</l>
               <l>Reſurget extrem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>Qui tranſmarinam navigan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbis ampli litt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra</l>
               <l>Expertus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnem novera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Terra mariſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſemitam,</l>
               <l>Tandem ſuam f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>licit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</l>
               <l>Mundi Chari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Adegit ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtum ratem,</l>
               <l>Sed vela jam ſi creditis</l>
               <l>Iterum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſe, &amp; ſua</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ediſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſa,</l>
               <l>Nec ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſan erit fides</l>
               <l>Ergo valete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Redibit, Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Gaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phyl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</l>
               <l>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:39"/>
               <l>Adnundi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as Hieruſalem</l>
               <l>Hic nobilis non civis est,</l>
               <l>At civis illic nobilis,</l>
               <l>Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lla datur hic aurea</l>
               <l>Illi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> gloria.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Henricus Noel.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:40"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ymbolum Honoratiſſimi D. Viceco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mitis <hi>Campden:</hi> optumi ſenis &amp; bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum patroni.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>NONDVM METAM.</head>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltu, Canitie, ſenio venerandus, &amp; annis,</l>
               <l>Et ſanus mente, &amp; corpore ſanus eras,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eltx progenie, felix vxore fuiſti,</l>
               <l>Externiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> potens afftuis, Euge! honis:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſatis haec non ſint, meritis &amp; honoribus auctus</l>
               <l>Diceris ipſe genus nobilitaſſe tuum.</l>
               <l>Quid! <hi>Nondum Metam</hi> ais? valde ampla eſt haec tibi meſſis.</l>
               <l>Aeger inops non es, ſed nec auarus eras:</l>
               <l>Quod ſivirtutem cupias, humilem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pium<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Nobilem &amp; humanum te, placidum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> virum,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntem, ſobrium celebramus, &amp; omnibus aequum,</l>
               <l>Et Regi gratum dicimus atque Deo.</l>
               <l>Quid ſupereſt ergo? quod ſupra eſt, inquis, in orbe</l>
               <l>Terrarum non eſt ſpes, neque meta mea,</l>
               <l>Non eſt haec infrà, coelis mihi meta repoſta,</l>
               <l>Chriſtus vbi viuit, regnat &amp; ipſe Deus;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic mea meta eſt, hic mea vita, hîc veta fuerunt:</l>
               <l>Non niſi per mortem huc tenditur? en morior.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>[Nondum Metan]</hi> vivus dixiſſe ſolebas;</l>
               <l>Sic <hi>Tandem Metam</hi> te tetigiſſe reor.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:3138:41"/>
               <head>De mortuis nil niſi bonum.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEe who was rich in bounty, as in wealth,</l>
                  <l>In honour humble, mindefull of his end,</l>
                  <l>Comely of perſon, full of dayes and health,</l>
                  <l>To rich and poore an amiable friend:</l>
                  <l>Enuy! thou knoweſt not him, if thou ſpeake ill,</l>
                  <l>Who neither liu'd, nor dyed againſt his will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aske not what workes of piety be did</l>
                  <l>Now when he dyed, his life was liberall,</l>
                  <l>From Church and Vniuerſity not hid:</l>
                  <l>He made leaſt noyſe when hee did moſt of all.</l>
                  <l>Giue me the prudent man, who while he liues</l>
                  <l>Doth his good workes; and ſo, ſees what he giues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He among men was iuſt, moſt free from wrong,</l>
                  <l>Sweet-natured, cheerefull, louing euery way,</l>
                  <l>To God deuout; his prayſes were his ſong;</l>
                  <l>His prayers, ſighes and teares: what ſhall I ſay?</l>
                  <l>This Lord is dead; and I am left, as one</l>
                  <l>Mong many, to be ſorry that hee's gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>W. B.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:41"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Age 2. line 10. for <hi>an hundred,</hi> reade <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: hundred,</hi> and l. 25. for <hi>things,</hi> reade <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> p. 21. l. 10. reade <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Catologue, for <hi>poore Priſoners,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Penſioners,</hi> in the verſes, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> reade <hi>atrae,</hi> for <hi>cinerem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> reade <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3138:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
